Preliminary Guide to the D. W. Newsom Papers, [ca. 1890]-1950 and undated RL.00944
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
D. W. Newsom papers
[ca. 1890]-1950 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Newsom, D. W. (Dallas Walton), 1873-1949
RL.00944
11.2 Linear Feet
2640 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The D. W. Newsom Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
Duke University alumnus (1899), as well as Trinity College Registrar (1901-1907) and Treasurer (1907-1923). Also, real estate and insurance agent (1923-1949), Durham County Commissioner (1924-1930), as well as the first Durham County Manager (1930-1943).
Collection Overview
Primarily incoming and outgoing personal and business correspondence, bills and receipts, bank statements, and deeds (1890-1950). The material documents Newsom's real estate activities and Durham N.C.'s economic and urban development from the 1920s-1940s. Also includes financial ledgers; scrapbooks of Newsom's newspaper real estate advertisements; notebooks in shorthand; various Newsom family estate papers; and a poem by Newsom, To the Men of the Golden Star, read by him at a World War I memorial service held at Trinity College (1919). The collection contains few records of Newsom's tenure as an official of Trinity College and Durham County. (02-102)
Real estate business -- North Carolina; Real property -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- Economic conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Scrapbooks; Business records -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Real estate agents -- North Carolina; Ledgers (account books); Deeds; Newsom, D. W. (Dallas Walton), 1873-1949; Newsom, D. W. (Dallas Walton), 1873-1949; Newsom family; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae
- Accession 2002-0102
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Newspapers, [ca. 1900] (Box 1)
    - Deeds of Trust and Bills of Sale, 1923-1929 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      [Includes one black-and-white photograph.]
    - Appraisal reports, 1929 (Box 1)
      [Newsom served as one of the appraisers reporting on the value of the properties belonging to the Duke Land and Improvement Company, New Hope Realty Company, in Durham.]
    - Personal notes (Box 1)
    - Durham County financial statements, 1933-1949 (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Receipts, 1949-1950, and tax returns, 1939-1944 (Box 2)
    - Receipts and invoices, 1930-1948 (Box 2)
      [Includes some from Newsom's tenure as Durham County Manager, but the majority are personal, including insurance payments and purchases from the bookstore, florist, etc. Also includes a series of loan passbooks from The Hood System Industrial Bank, Durham, NC.]
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Receipts and Invoices, 1928-1948 (Box 3)
    - Incoming and outgoing correspondence, 1929-1948 (Box 3)
      [The majority of the letters deal with loans and loan payments and real estate property. A few are from family.]
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Incoming and outgoing business correspondence, 1928-1948 (Box 4)
      [Includes a few letters mentioning Mr. Newsom's poetry.]
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Incoming and outgoing correspondence, including real estate deeds, 1890-1948 (Box 5)
    - Shorthand notes (Box 5)
    - Durham real estate and other ephemera (Box 5)
      [Includes Newsom's business card and several programs from conventions of the North Carolina Real Estate Association.]
    - Poems and prose
      - To the Men of the Golden Star (Box 5)
        [Read by Newsom at a World War I memorial service held at Trinity College, 1919 June 3.]
      - The History of Duke Memorial Methodist Episcopal Church, South (Box 5)
        [Read by Newsom 1932 October 30 at Duke Memorial Methodist Episcopal Church.]
    - Renters' and owners' invoices, bank statements, and other real estate documents, 1926-1932 (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    - Newsom estate documents, [ca. 1908] (Box 6)
    - Shorthand notes (Box 6)
    - Personal notebooks (Box 6)
      [Many are in shorthand.]
    - 1942 Date Book (Box 6)
      [Contains various Christmas card lists, Christmas gift lists, and Christmas expenditures from 1937-1946.]
    - Ernest H. Newsom estate papers, [ca. 1910] (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Financial ledgers and journals, 1902-1946 (Box 7)
    - Personal correspondence from Jottings binder, [ca. 1917-1945] (Box 7)
    - Medical records, 1949 (Box 7)
      [Includes a daily log of Newsom's health during the final year of his life.]
  - Contents of box 8: (Box 8)
    - Two scrapbooks containing Newsom's Bulletin, 1923-1928 (Box 8)
      Newsom's weekday real estate newspaper advertisements. Also includes the Sunday Newsom's Bulletin, 1927-1928, which consisted of short inspirational statements.
  - Contents of box 9: (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, [1909]-[ca. 1940s] (Box 9)
      Includes news and inspirational quotations apparently collected by Newsom.
  - Contents of box 10: (Box 10)
    - Financial ledger showing Newsom's income and expenses, [1904]-[1920s] (Box 10)
    - Financial ledger [showing Newsom's rental expenses], 1923-1924 (Box 10)
      Includes examples of Newsom's stationery, laid in.
    - Two signs, For Rent, D. W. Newsom, Phone F-5311 (Box 10)
  - Contents of oversize folder 1: (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Plans for D.W. Newsom house, Trinity College, Durham, NC (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Plans for residential development of Fort Fisher-Sea Beach, [NC], 1913 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Contents of oversize folder 2: (Oversize-folder 2)
    - Plans for residential development of Fort Fisher-Sea Beach, [NC], 1913 (Oversize-folder 2)
    - Linen map and blueprint, Mrs. Annie Soule Newsom Estate, Halifax Co., 1909 (Oversize-folder 2)